<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A representation to the High Court of Parliament, of some of the most palpable grievances in the Colledge of Justice, (both as to its constitution and administration) and several members thereof.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1689</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 32 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B04980</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R1109B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R182675</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">51617488</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 51617488</idno>
            <idno type="VID">175336</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B04980)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 175336)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2730:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A representation to the High Court of Parliament, of some of the most palpable grievances in the Colledge of Justice, (both as to its constitution and administration) and several members thereof.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>J. Reid?,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1689]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint details suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: tightly bound with some loss of text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the National Library of Scotland.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Scotland. --  Court of Session.</term>
               <term>Lawyers --  Scotland --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Scotland --  Politics and government --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:175336:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:175336:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A Repreſentation to the High Court of PARLIAMENT, of ſome of the moſt <hi>Palpable Grievances</hi> in the <hi>COLLEDGE</hi> of <hi>JUSTICE,</hi> (both as to its Conſtitution and Adminiſtration) and ſeveral Members thereof.</head>
            <p>IT is evident from the whole Tract and Current of our Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes and Records, that the King's Council were firſt Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tut the Supreme Judges in all Civil Cauſes, and that the Council was Nominat and appointed (for adviſing the King in all matters of State and others) by His Great Court of <hi>Parliament:</hi> But by the 65. <hi>Act,</hi> Par. 3. <hi>James</hi> 1. It is Statute that there be ſome Commiſſioners of Parliament choſen <hi>per vices,</hi> who with the Chancellor ſhall ſit at three times in the year, for cognoſcing and Determining of all Cauſes, that were formerly cognoſced by the King or his Council, and who were alſo called <hi>Lords of Seſſion,</hi> as is clear by the <hi>Act</hi> 61. <hi>par.</hi> 14. <hi>Ja.</hi> 2. Of which Judicature ſo Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute, there was ſmall or no Alteration until the 36. <hi>Act,</hi> 5. <hi>par. Ja.</hi> 5. Whereby in place of the ſaid <hi>Committee of Parliament,</hi> there is a fixt <hi>Colledge of Juſtice</hi> Inſtitute, to conſiſt of Fourteen able Qualfied Perſons, and a Preſident; And for declaring their Qualifications and prefixing Rules for Adminiſtration of <hi>Juſtice,</hi> the whole ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent Acts of that Parliament were made; And by the 68. <hi>Act</hi> thereof, there is ſeveral Priviledges and Immunities granted to the ſaids <hi>Lords</hi> as is at length therein contained, and by the 93. <hi>Act</hi> of the 7. <hi>Parliament</hi> of the ſaid King, theſe priviledges are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain ratified, and the <hi>Popes</hi> Approbation and Confirmation there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and which is alſo ratified by Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> Parliament 2. <hi>Cap.</hi> 1. and <hi>James</hi> the 6. <hi>Parliament</hi> 1. <hi>Cap.</hi> 18. And by many other ſubſequent Acts of his, and all other <hi>Parliaments;</hi> All which do ſtill go on in the ſtyle of ratifying and approving of the foreſaids Priviledges. But till this day never any Reſtrictions or Limita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions put either upon their Nominations or exerciſing the ſaid Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, which has been got waved by the Intereſt of theſe who were Nominat and in Office, and their Sway and Power which they had in all Succeeding Councils and Parliaments, whereof many of them were alſo ordinarly Members. So that their power is of a long time come almoſt to be <hi>Arbitrary.</hi> Seeing they aſſume not
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:175336:2"/> only the Power of making Acts of <hi>Sederunt,</hi> whereupon ſome of the greateſt Eſtates and Securities of the Nation are now founded, but alſo to expound clear Acts of <hi>Parliament,</hi> expreſly contrair the poſitive words thereof, which is in effect to repeal the ſamen, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by aſſuming the <hi>Legiſlative</hi> Power, ſince <hi>ejus eſt interpretare cujus eſt tondere:</hi> And albeit they might pretend they could not other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes explicat their Juriſdiction, and whatever they might claim right to, during the interval of Parliaments, yet after they are incited and ſitting, all ſuch Acts and Interpretations ought to have a Parliamentary Sanction and Ratification, other wayes to have been lookt upon, as deeds not Approveable by the States, nor Wiſdom and Juſtice of the Nation: And all this was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted by the Learned and Sagacious <hi>Buchannan,</hi> who in the 14. Book of his Hiſtory near the end thereof, does expreſs himſelf in thir Terms; <hi>Quo die collegium Judicum Edinburgi conſtititum eſt ab its, cum ab initio multa utiliter eſſent ex cogitata ut jus equabile Diceretur, tamen qui ſperabatur eventus non eſt confecutus. Nam cum in Scotia nullae pene ſint Leges, praeter conventuum decreta, eaque pleraque non in perpetuum, ſed in tempus facta, judiceſque, quod in ſe eſt, lationem legum impediant, omnium <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ium bona Quindecim hominum arbitrio ſunt commiſſa quibus &amp; perpetua eſt poteſtas, &amp; Imperium plane Tyrannicum: Quippe, quorum ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitria ſola ſunt pro legibus.</hi> I think it not fit to Tranſlate it in <hi>Engliſh,</hi> leaſt the Vulgar ſhould be tempted to look upon him as a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet.</p>
            <p>It may be therefore juſtly thought, that in this healing Jun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture, there be a ſlender Repreſentation made of ſuch things, as ſeem to be palpable grounds of Grievance in that Court, in the right Conſtitution and Adminiſtration whereof, all perſons from higheſt to the loweſt are, or may be eminently and dearly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned; Seeing their Lives and Fortunes, may become the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of their conſideration, and therefore there can be nothing more acceptable to the People, or worthy the trouble of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentatives of the Nation, nor to redreſs what may be amiſs therein, and ſeing in many things the ſame is faulty both as to its Conſtitution and Inhability of the Members, as alſo in the male Adminiſtration though rightly conſtitute, thir Points are offered as worthy Conſideration, Relative to the <hi>Lords, Advocats,</hi> and <hi>Kings Advocat, Lord Regiſter,</hi> and <hi>Clerks</hi> of Inner and Utter Houſe;
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:175336:2"/> And alſo an hint of ſome particular Grievances, of which in Order,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Primo,</hi> Seeing by the Laws of all Nations, and in ſpecial by the <hi>Act</hi> 134. <hi>Par.</hi> 12. <hi>Ja.</hi> 6. It is thereby Statute that to all <hi>Vacati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in Seſſion,</hi> none ſhall be preſented, but Men fearing GOD, of good Learning, Knowledge, and Practick of the Laws, and hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſufficient living of their own; and farther that none be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, unleſs they be ſufficiently tryed and known by the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Lords,</hi> and have in yearly Rent an 1000. <hi>Merks,</hi> or 20. <hi>chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of Victual;</hi> If in Juſtice or Law any ought to be admitted to that Function but ſuch as Quadrat therewith, the ſamen never being yet repealled by any Act of Parliament, whatever Viola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions or Subverſions have been made thereof, by unjuſt ſtreat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches and Court Recommendations, whereby perſons have been thruſt into that Office, whoſe Inclinations not Education did ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver Level at the meaneſt Imployment in that Court. And it ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived to that height of Indifference, what perſons were admitted to that Office, that it was the ordinar Aſſurance to ſuch as the Court intended to gratifie, that they ſhould either be one of the <hi>Lords of Seſſion,</hi> or a Captain of <hi>Foot,</hi> (a pretty Alternative indeed) as was lately propoſed to a Gentleman, to move him to end a Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan, with an then Eminent Stateſman.</p>
            <p n="2">2do. Seeing that the puting of Perſons in that Office not quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied as ſaid is, muſt inevitably occaſion great purloining and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laying of <hi>Juſtice,</hi> to the prejudice and ruine (if not all) at leaſt of many who ſhall come to have Dependencies before them. If it be not therefore the Concern of the States and People, that not only the ſaid Law be brought in Obſervance, but ſome new <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi> ſuperaded thereto, that may make the ſamen more effectual; And in ſpecial, that ſeeing we are now come to that conſiſtance, as to have many Subtilities and Niceties both in our <hi>Statutes, Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes</hi> and <hi>Practicks,</hi> that none be admitted to the ſaids Offices, but ſuch (beſide what is above mentioned) as have alſo been Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gally admitted <hi>Advocats,</hi> according to the uſual forms of Tryal; and have practiſed ſeveral years therein Candidly, and with that Integrity and Ability which ought to be Indiſpenſably requiſite in a perſon to be promoted to the foreſaid Station, and by this the <hi>Bench</hi> will as well have a Natural, as a Legal Supperiotity to
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:175336:3"/> the <hi>Barr:</hi> For it cannot but be thought that Mens Abilities are much miſplaced, when the Reaſons of theſe at the <hi>Barr,</hi> are too ſtrong for theſe who are to Judge of them. The Diſcovery where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, will force that Reſpect to be transferred to the <hi>Barr,</hi> which ought to be payed to the <hi>Bench,</hi> and make <hi>Clients murmure</hi> when that which is proponed for them, is not diſcuſt with Reaſons ſui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to theſe alledged in their Favours; And tho at firſt Fifteen was a ſufficient number, for all the matters that then did occur, yet now ſeeing there is at leaſt ten Cauſes for one, and <hi>Lawyers</hi> are arived to that pitch of Debating, both with greater Accuratneſs and length; Nor was at the Infancie of the ſaid <hi>Colledge,</hi> that it may ſeem rational that the number of the <hi>Lords</hi> ſhould be augmented, &amp; that none of them ſhold be Members of any other Court, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to divert their Attendance; And if any thing occur in other Courts, as in <hi>Council</hi> or <hi>Exchequer,</hi> that requires the opinion of <hi>Lawyers,</hi> (which was the firſt pretences for putting ſome of them there) that the opinion of the whole <hi>Lords</hi> be taken thereanent, and not to be determined by any particular one, that may chance to ſit there.</p>
            <p n="3">3tio. Theſe admitted to the ſaid Office, being only <hi>Lawyers</hi> of known Ability and Integrity, if it be not fit that they preſide <hi>per vices,</hi> at the leaſt, that nine of them (which by our Law is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared to be the <hi>Quorum</hi> of the <hi>Seſſion</hi>) may be capable of that Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice. Whereby there will great Advantage accreſs to the Leiges, ſeeing there will be greater diſpatch of Juſtice; (throw delay whereof moſt perſons are ruined) For none will deny conſidering the preſent throng of Affairs,) but that it is impoſſible that one ſingle perſon can digeſtedly conſider, not only all the Cauſes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate <hi>in preſentia,</hi> but alſo twenty or thirty <hi>Prolix Bills,</hi> and tedious <hi>Informations</hi> of cauſes to be reported in one day, which muſt either be fully digeſted by him, or the matter will be only Superficially ſcruified over, which gives als great ground of new Billing or informing as if the matter had never been heard: And <hi>Preſident Stair</hi> for himſelf, in the Epiſtle Dedicatory to the firſt volume of his <hi>Practicks;</hi> Declares that the uneaſineſs thereof made him to quite that Office, which he obſerved to have ſunk <hi>Sir John Gillmor</hi> his predeceſſor a man of great ſtrength, both of Body and Spirit: Likeas, albeit there were not the inconvenience foreſaid
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:175336:3"/> in the conſtancie thereof, which is ſufficient to enforce an Altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; Yet the Leiges are not ſo fully ſecured in point of Juſtice, becauſe the fixing the <hi>Preſidency</hi> in one, makes ſuch an unequal Ballance in that Court, that what ever ſide he ſhall favour or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline to, is almoſt certain to carry the cauſe; Whereas if it be lodged in a <hi>Plurality,</hi> or in them all by turns, there will be no ſuch hazard; And it is commonly received that <hi>Plures Difficilius co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rumpuntur quam pautiores,</hi> and that <hi>plus vident oculi quam oculus:</hi> From all which it is moſt conſequential both from <hi>Reaſon, Juſtice</hi> and the <hi>Practick</hi> of other Nations, that either the Office be Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culat among all, or the Plurality thereof, as ſaid is</p>
            <p n="4">4to. Seeing great inconveniencie and confuſion does ariſe throw the adviſing of Cauſes, receiving of Reports, and reading of Bills with cloſs doors, neither Parties nor Advocats being allowed to be preſent, whereby there is great miſtakes at the time of adviſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Cauſes, where the <hi>Probation</hi> is by an great number of Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, or by many ſeveral Writs, which is only overly read by the <hi>Clerk,</hi> which occaſions great miſtakes in the <hi>Lords,</hi> whom that part in the Witneſſes Depoſitions which evinces the <hi>Proban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum</hi> have eſcaped, eſpecially where it may be Culled only out of two, of twenty: And the like may be alſo ſaid, where many writes are produced for proving; Whereas if matters were adviſed with open doors, and <hi>Advocats</hi> preſent who have ſeriouſly conſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the ſamen, it would be eaſy for them to point out to the <hi>Lords,</hi> the particular Teſtimonies and Clauſes of Writs; or the parts thereof that do evince what is to be proven: And as for the taking in Reports of Cauſes debate in the utter Houſe, the incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniencie is yet greater; ſeeing it is <hi>Notture</hi> (as having dayly oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured) that where there are ſeveral points to be reported, ſome of them are omitted, yea even where there is but one, yet if it be ſo far followed in the Debate, as to come the length of <hi>Triples,</hi> or <hi>Quadruples,</hi> ſome of theſe, at leaſt the principal Reaſons enfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing, the Relevancy thereof will alſo be omitted, and which are the occaſions of the many numerous Bills, which are dayly gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven into rectifie ſuch miſtakes; And which would be altogether needleſs, if things were done with open doors, in preſence of <hi>Parties</hi> and <hi>Procurators,</hi> as ſaid is: And which is the known Practiſe of moſt (if not all) other Nations.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:175336:4"/>
            <p n="5">5to. All the Premiſſes being thus rectified; If it be not both Juſt and expedient, that <hi>Extrajudicial Soliſtations</hi> be diſcharged, either by the Clients, or any other perſon, who may be thought to have Intereſt in, or Influence upon the Judge, and that under the Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification that it ſhall be equal to <hi>Bribery,</hi> if the Judge ſhall wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly receive the ſamen, and if the Party or any from him ſhall obtrude it, that either he ſhall <hi>cadere cauſa,</hi> or at leaſt the Judge ſhall be incapable to vote in that cauſe, which as it is Juſt and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient: So it is Conſonant to the Act of <hi>Sederunt,</hi> made againſt <hi>Soliſtations,</hi> 6. <hi>November,</hi> 1677. And the Practice of all other Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, where <hi>Soliſting</hi> is lookt upon as equal to corrupting.</p>
            <p n="6">6to. That in regard the Sons and Brethren of the Judges, are ordinarly imployed upon the preſumption of the ſuppoſed Influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, that they may have upon or ready acceſs to him. That therefore none be allowed to Judge, or ſingly to Cognoſce any cauſe, where ſuch Dependents or Relations are imployed as <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocats</hi> or <hi>Agents;</hi> And that it ſhall be a ſufficient Declinator of the Judge, that any ſuch was imployed in it.</p>
            <p>It may be alſo thought moſt improper, (if not Abſurd) that the <hi>Clerk</hi> of <hi>Regiſter</hi> ſhould be an ordinar Judge, as one of the <hi>Lords of Seſſion;</hi> For it was never heard, nor is it conſiſtent with the Conſtitution of any Court, that one perſon ſhould both be Clerk and Judge therein, and the common <hi>Brocard of Law</hi> is, that <hi>Judex &amp; Clericus faciunt forum,</hi> which ſtates them as clear diſtinct Offices; and it is as incongruous as for one Man both to be <hi>Clerk</hi> &amp; <hi>Advocat:</hi> For the Clerk is truly the common Truſty of the Court, for writting and putting in Record what is there Debate and decern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; And which after it is put in an Act or Decreet, can neither be recalled nor redargued (if fairly done) either by the Judge or Advocat: So that he is Check to both, yea he thereby ſo fixes himſelf, as that he can neither innovat nor alter what is Extract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and done; And the Law expreſly ſayes, <hi>nec credendum Judici, nec clerico, niſi quatenus conſtat ex actis;</hi> ſo that there can be nothing more groſs, nor to lodge the two Offices of being Clerk &amp; Judge in one Perſon. Nor does his Greatneſs and Multiplicity of Offices ſtop here, but he is <hi>Clerk</hi> of <hi>Parliaments</hi> and <hi>Conventions,</hi> and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him depends all the ſix <hi>Clerks</hi> of <hi>Seſſion; Clerk</hi> of the <hi>Bills, Clerks</hi> of the Regiſter of <hi>Seaſins, Clerk</hi> to the Regiſter of <hi>Hornings, Clerk</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:175336:4"/> of <hi>Chequer, Clerk</hi> to the Admiſſion of the whole <hi>Nottars</hi> of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, together with many others which I here omitt. And moſt of theſe being Offices wherein things paſs of Courſe, and have Emoluments that might gratifie very conſiderable perſons; Yet are all ſwallowed up by this <hi>Leviathan,</hi> which therefore ought to be divided, and theſe intruſted to depend immediately upon his Majeſtie. Eſpecially ſeeing there is now ſo many men, and yet few imployments, being abſorbed by the exorbitant Extent of this, and ſome other ſuch Offices.</p>
            <p>As to <hi>Advocats</hi> what and how Honourable that Office is, the <hi>Encomia</hi> given and priviledges granted by the <hi>Emperors</hi> thereto, does ſufficiently demonſtrat with what reſpect it was lookt upon by them: For <hi>Theodoſius</hi> and <hi>Valentinian</hi> by a Novel Conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, expreſt themſelves to this purpoſe; <hi>Let thoſe who deſerves to be Advocats be eſteemed worthy of all Honour, for what Honour can we Judge theſe unworthy of, who by their Life and Eloquence, preſerves not only the Republick, but the private Intereſt and lives of Perſons.</hi> And the Emperor <hi>Leo,</hi> farther adds, in thir words, <hi>Suaeque defenſionis viribus ſepe publicis in rebus, ac privatis lapſa erigunt fatigata reparant, non minus provident humano generi, quam ſi preliis atque vulneribus patriam pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renteſque ſalvarent clariſſimis anumerantur militumque privilegiis frunutur.</hi> That therefore none be admitted to that Office, but ſuch as paſs the ordinar Tryal by publick and private Examinations and Leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and that it be declared not to be leiſome for the Lords to admit any upon Bills, under the pain of amitting an years Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lary. Likeas that it ſhall be a ſufficient Defence for any party againſt whom any ſuch Advocat ſhall be imployed, that he was not Legally admitted, as ſaid is.</p>
            <p>It is evident to the World, how far this Nation has degenerat, not only from the practice of the <hi>common Law,</hi> eſpecially <hi>Imperial Roman Conſtitution;</hi> But alſo from its own Cuſtoms and Statutes foreſaid, made at the Inſtitution of the <hi>Colledge of Juſtice,</hi> and the Cuſtome and Practice of all other well governed Nations; That by Court recommendations, or particular Favour or Intereſt in ſome ſingle Senator. Theſe whoſe Education had never any tendency that way; but on the contrare were educate for Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, Merchants and other ſuch Extranious Employments, after they were diſcouraged in theſe, were admitted to the ſaid Office,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:175336:5"/> ſummarly upon a Bill, without any previous Tryal, either of their Ability or Integrity. And ſeing they had neither Art nor Merit, whereby to promote their Intereſt by fair Means, and having undertaken the ſamen, of purpoſe to reap Advantage there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, it cannot be imagined how theſe Deſignes ſhould be effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuate, but by abuſing that Truſt, which ſome of the Ignorant might repoſe in them, and by whom daily Clamours are made, that they are cheated and abuſed by their Lawyers, which to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decerning Hearers is a reflection, upon that Noble Office, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the Actors are ſuch as never did merit that Deſignation: And what can be imagined to have been the Deſign of ſuch Recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendations and Admiſſions, but that there might be plyable Men put in to ſerve ſome State turn; That when thoſe who were in Office refuſed to ſolve according to their Inclination, what ſhould be propoſed, but that ſuch as were reaſtie ſhould be turned out, and ſuch put in their places as would give opinions at their diſcretion, as theſe Judges in <hi>England</hi> had done, thereby to give a Colour of Law for their Proceedings, to the amuſing of the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decerning People.</p>
            <p>What ever latitude might have been taken by the Lords in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer times, yet it ought not now to be aſſumed. <hi>Primo,</hi> Becauſe by the 64. <hi>Act, Par.</hi> 5. <hi>Ja.</hi> 5. Whereby the particular perſons therein mentioned are ordained to be <hi>Procurators,</hi> and the motive is ſaid to be that they are men of beſt Name, Knowledge and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, and thereafter is ſubjoyned that if any other Cunning Men would deſire to admitted to that Office, they ſhould be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived for compleating the ſaid number, ſo that the Lords are there limited by that firſt Fundamental Law, ſo that none be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, but ſuch as are cunning, that is to ſay, are Men of Art, Knowledge and Experience, 2do. Albeit there might have been ſome Latitude, taken by the Lords in admitting of perſons not qualified, at the Infancie of the Colledge, when few were educate for that Employment: Yet now when the number of ſuch is ſo increſſed, far above what is neceſſar, and theſe Men of Literature, Integrity and Quality, It is not only unjuſt and unwarrantable in it ſelf ſummarly, without Tryal to admit others, as ſaid is; But is alſo Diſcouraging and Diſadvantagious to thoſe young Gentlemen, who has ſpent their Time and Eſtates at home or
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:175336:5"/> abroad, in fitting themſelves to ſerve in that Imployment.</p>
            <p n="3">3tio. Seing there is ſo many Perſons who have Proſecute that Study, ſo as that upon Tryal they may be juſtly admitted, yet ſeeing the number has ſo increaſed and multiplyed of late, that there can not be ſuitable Encouragments expected for all, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by ſome may be tempted to ungenerous Courſes and Practices, ſuch as Inſtigating or buying of Pleas, or the like; That therefore the number be retrinched to Fourty or Fifty, and that none be admitted but upon their Deceaſe, and that theſe who are tryed and ready to be admitted, ſerve as Agents and Extrajudicial Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagers of Proceſs, and that all others be ſecluded, but ſuch as have ſtudied the Laws, and are ready to be admitted upon Vacan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, whereby alſo theſe who have aſſumed (without any previous tryal) the name of Agents will be ſecluded and rendered uſeleſs; And the Laws already made diſcharging them, will thereby be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come effectual.</p>
            <p n="4">4to. Seeing the ſaid Imployment is dignified by the <hi>Encomia</hi> and priviledges foreſaid, and that they differ from the <hi>Lords,</hi> not in Kind but Degree; That therefore according to the Cuſtome of <hi>France, England,</hi> and other Neighbour Nations they be covered when they plead, and that the mutual Compellations be ſuch as is uſed there, ſeeing otherwiſe the moſt Eminent <hi>Advocats</hi> ſhall have no Priviledge, above what is allowed their Servants</p>
            <p>It cannot be denyed but the <hi>Colledge of Juſtice</hi> was long Inſtitute, before there was any particular perſon appointed to be <hi>Kings Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocat;</hi> and the firſt appointed was in Queen <hi>Mary's</hi> Minority, at which time there was but very few Affairs that did occur, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in her <hi>Majeſties Advocat</hi> might be concerned: So that tho one was at that time ſufficient, and the intereſt of the perſons Nominat, ſince has been always ſo great with the King and Court, that it has been als eaſy to turn them out, as to procure the leaſt Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration thereof, but now in this Age when Pleas are increaſed and multiplied, to Ten for One moe nor was at the ſaid firſt Appointment; Eſpecially ſuch wherein his <hi>Majeſties Advocat</hi> is principally concerned, as Riots, private crimes, open Rebellions, beſides many other Civil caiſes unheard of at that time. That therefore his Majeſties intereſt, and of the State, (whereof he is an Officer) ſhould now at leaſt be lodged in three or four, pickt
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:175336:6"/> out by the States for that effect. <hi>Primo,</hi> Becauſe not only are mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters multiplied as ſaid is; So that it is impoſſible for any ſingle perſon to exerciſe the ſamen, but either with loſs to his Majeſty by neglect of what ought to be done, or doing what ought not to be done; as by intending Malitious and groundleſs Proceſſes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Subjects; Whereas if the Office were Collegiat in a num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of fit and Qualified perſons, It were not to be feared but upon joynt adviſing, they would diſcover what Proceſſes were ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Vexations and State ſtreaches, ſo as they would be choak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Bud. 2ly, It can be made appear that in the year 1683. and 1684. when moſt of the Heretors and Inhabitants of the <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ern Shires,</hi> were either cited in as Pannals or Witneſſes, for prov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Reſet or Converſe, and others the like Crimes, who would have attended ſome twenty, ſome fourty or ſixty dayes, before they could be got examined by the Advocat, who was otherwiſe taken up in <hi>Seſſion, Council, Exchequer,</hi> or other Courts, whereby theſe Shires are conjectured to have been at the Expence in ſome few years, of upwards of 300000. <hi>Merks,</hi> in ſimple attending at <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> which was occaſioned by the being of one ſingle Advo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat as ſaid is. 3tio, As the ſtating that Office in moe, would be Advantagious both to His Majeſtie and the Leiges for the Reaſon foreſaid, ſo alſo upon this ground, that thereby each of them might have their proper Poſts, <hi>viz.</hi> One for the <hi>Council</hi> and matters of State, an other for the <hi>Exchequer</hi> and matters of Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue, a third for the <hi>Juſtice Court,</hi> and the fourth for the <hi>Seſſion</hi> and Commiſſion of the Kirk; yet not ſo to be poſted as one of them to exclude another, but that the perſons concerned might Addreſs equally to them all, and this would alſo ſecure the Leid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, againſt the inconveniency that attends the fixing this Office in one ſingle Perſon, which makes them frequently both Arbitra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and unacceſſible; Beſides that it has all the Grievances which can accrue from a Monopoly, which is Reprobate in all Law. 4to, In Neighbouring <hi>Sciences,</hi> ſuch as <hi>Divines, Phyſicians,</hi> His Majeſty has alwayes three of four at leaſt; and there is grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ground for multiplying of Perſons in this Office. 5to, It will nothing add to the charge of his Majeſties Expence, ſeeing thir many years by paſt, the Sallarie and Penſion allowed to that Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, may be ſufficient Competencie tho divided in four, ſeeing
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:175336:6"/> they will alſo remain Advocats for the Leiges, and whoſe Imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment will center to them upon that account: In reſpect of all which there ought if not four to be at leaſt two, as has been in ſome former times, with two <hi>Solicitors.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As to the Clerks of the Inner and Utterhouſe, as all Men in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick office ought not only by our Law, but by the rules of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon prudence and Juſtice, to be perſons or known Ability and Integrity; It being impoſſible if they be otherways, but that the Leidges muſt egregiouſly ſuffer either by their Ignorance or fraud, conſidering how many occaſions they have to trincket (if they be baſe) they having the cuſtody of the Securities of the Nation, and thereby become Maſters of many of the ſecrets of their Affairs, and who may add or omitt both in Interloquitors and Deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances of Bills, which may chance to be the ground of an extract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Decreet, againſt which our Law has ſmall or no remed, unleſs the abuſe of the Clerk and the injuſtice of the thing it ſelf be moſt groſs and palpable, and even when it is ſuch, Perſons are put to a vaſt charge, trouble and expence in clearing thereof and in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing reponed againſt the ſamen, ſo that means ought to be fallen upon, for crubbihg of ſuch intollerable Practices, which may ſo overawe, as that none may hereafter darr to commit the like, and that whatever may be detected which may be groſs and willful, that thereupon Deprivation (at the leaſt) be inflicted.</p>
            <p n="2">2do. That none be admitted <hi>per ſaltum</hi> to the ſaid Office, unleſs they have gradually aſcended, from being ſome competent time Educat in <hi>Clerks Chambers,</hi> or that they have been practiſing <hi>Advo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cats,</hi> Writers to the <hi>Signet,</hi> or the like.</p>
            <p n="3">3tio. As to their Fies and Allowances the exorbitancie thereof, are ſo many and Noture, eſpecially ſince the <hi>Act of Regulation</hi> 1672. that it is fit there be Commiſſions renewed for rectifying there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; And albeit ſuch have been granted by ſeveral <hi>Parliaments</hi> ſince, yet ſo far have theſe in Office prevailed for ſhifting thereof, that the perſons were never yet condeſcended upon, to have been inſert in theſe Commiſſions, and the Acts were <hi>Printed blank</hi> contrair to all former Laws and Practick of the Nation, whereby the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons Names are alwayes ingroſſed in the Acts and Printed, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, and particular dyets appointed for that effect, to be keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed under ſevere Penalties, elſe the Law is only rendered <hi>redicule,</hi> as wanting Certification or <hi>Compulſorial.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:175336:7"/>
            <p>Theſe being ſome of the general Grievances, whereof the O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure &amp; throng of a Parliament can only be expected to judge <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> there are many others which may truely and fitly be given <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> any Commiſſion that ſhall be appointed for the effect; Such <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to make effectual Laws for diſcharging the <hi>Syde Bar; Item,</hi> To <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viate the binding officious Compearances in Decreets, (by <hi>Advo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates</hi>) upon the Lieges whereby many of them have been high<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> prejudged, when <hi>Advocates</hi> did either of themſelves, or at the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of Agents, or others, take dayes for Defenders, to give th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> Oaths in ordinar Actions, or to produce Writes in Improbatio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And whereof the Client was never Advertiſed, but Sentence <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> out againſt them, and which is irrevockable in our Law. T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> therefore in theſe and ſuch like caſes, the Compearer ought <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> have a <hi>Written Mandate,</hi> at the leaſt Papers in his hands, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> import the ſamen. <hi>Item,</hi> How far Clerks ſhall be lyable for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> produced to them, and how long. <hi>Item,</hi> How long <hi>Writes</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>duced be the Defenders in Reductions and Improbations, oug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> to lye in the Clerks hands, ſeing many of them are miſcart<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> by lying too long therein. <hi>Item,</hi> If the Principals be once <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced, ſo that the Purſuers may either take Doubles, or N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> thereof, if they ought to be again produced, untill the Cauſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Adviſed. <hi>Item,</hi> That the Money lying in the Clerk to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Hands, as the Expence modified at ſuſpending inferiour Decr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> and Proteſtation Money, and others of the like nature not ra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> up by the Parties, be given up for advancing the Library of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Faculty. <hi>Item,</hi> That the Commiſſars and Sheriff-Deputes be cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen of theſe <hi>Advocates,</hi> who will be laid aſide upon the Reſtriction of their number to fourty or fifty, as ſaid is: Theſe and in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> numbers of others of the like nature, which may be both re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to, and regulated by the Commiſſion which may be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for that effect I here commit until the Parliament ſo think fit, to appoint the ſame, to conſiſt partly of Perſons of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſeveral Offices within the ſaid Court, who beſt knows what is to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Rectified therein, and may be the fitteſt mutual Checks to other.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
